let's assume that we have one process process
0 that
takes 100 seconds to finish but also has to
do one input
output every second
so not really that frequently
and then we have another 1000 processes and
they need to
perform 1000 input/output operations each
if we use first come first serve then we start
with process
0 this will take 1000 seconds to finish
every time process 0 requests an input
output and goes
into waiting
we have the chance to run the next process
processes 1 to 1000 get to perform one input/output
every second
they need 1000 I/O requests
they are going to perform 1000 I/O requests
which
implies that it will take for them 16 minutes
more than 16
minutes to finish (1000 seconds)
on the other hand if we use a preemptive strategy
we could
preempt process zero every
10 milliseconds
and let the other processes run
since they have mainly I/O requests and they
are I/O
bound they would rapidly go into waiting
so from the perspective of process zero it
would still
more or less take 1000 second to finish
because what takes time in process zero is
the second of
CPU time it spends every time on the other
end
from the perspective of processes from 1 to
1000 they would
complete in 10 seconds
so you can see that it's significantly better
in this case
to use of preemptive strategy
for their scheduling